Inventory of Norman David Hanwell papers,
Hoover Institution Archives
Norman David Hanwell papers
1928-1944
2015C15
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, notes, and printed matter relating to political and social conditions in China during the 1930s, the Communist movement in China in the 1930s, and the Sino-Japanese War.
Hanwell, Norman David, 1909-1941.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical note
Norman David Hanwell was a China scholar whose research interests included Chinese Communism, guerilla warfare, Chinese villages, Sino-Japanese relations, and Japanese aggressions in China in the 1930s. His articles appeared in publications such as the Christian Science Monitor, Herald Tribune, Asia Magazine, and The Nation.
Hanwell was born on February 20, 1909 in San Francisco, California. He married Dorothea Smith in 1937, and the couple moved to China in 1939. Hanwell died of a heart infection on October 5, 1941 in Peking, China
Scope and Contents
The collection is composed of correspondence, writings, notes, and printed matter relating to political and social conditions in China during the 1930s, the Communist movement in China in the 1930s, and the Sino-Japanese War.
China--History--1928-1937.; China--History--1937-1945.; Communism--China.; Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945.
- Correspondence, 1934-1939
  - Amerasia, 1937 (Text 1: 1)
  - American Council of the Institute of Pacific Relations, 1937-1938 (Text 1: 2)
  - Asia Magazine (Henrietta Gerwig, Richard Walsh), 1936-1939 (Text 1: 3)
  - Christian Science Monitor, 1935 (Text 1: 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes photos of Yun Kang caves.
  - Dorothea Gabel Coryell, 1935-1937 (Text 1: 5)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes encounters with Ed Snow, Owen Lattimore, and Agnes Smedley.
  - Dorothea Gabel Coryell, 1938 (Text 1: 6)
  - Los Angeles Times, 1934 (Text 1: 7)
    Includes articles written on the Jiangxi Campaign.
  - Maxwell Stewart, The Nation, 1936 (Text 1: 8)
  - Mortimer Graves (American Council of Learned Societies), 1934-1937 (Text 1: 9)
  - Pacific Affairs, 1937-1938 (Text 1: 10)
  - University of Minnesota, 1937 (Text 1: 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1935-1937 (Text 1: 12)
- Printed Materials, 1931-1944
  - "Aids to the Study of Chinese Philosophy", 1934 (Text 1: 13)
  - China Today, 1937 (Text 1: 14)
  - Contemporary Japan (Index), 1935-1936 (Text 1: 15)
  - Conference for University Men, Council on Foreign Relations, 1937 (Text 1: 16)
  - Democracy, 1937 (Text 2: 1)
  - "Essentials of Chinese Drama", 1935 (Text 2: 2)
  - Fortnightly Survey of Current Events, Council of International Affairs, 1935-1938 (Text 2: 3)
  - Japan's militarism clippings, 1936 (Text 2: 4)
  - Information Bulletin, Council of International Affairs, China, 1937 (Box-folder 2: 5-8)
  - "Sino-Japanese Conflicts in Northern China", 1931-1942 (Text 2: 9)
  - "The Far East - A Syllabus", by George L. Harris, 1944 (Text 2: 10)
  - "Topical Analysis of Comparative European Government", by Joseph R. Starr, 1936 (Text 2: 11)
- Research and Notes, 1928-1938
  - Chinese-language clippings on agriculture and 1931 Beijing student strike (Text 3: 1)
  - Clippings: Civil War in China, 1934-1938 (Text 3: 2)
  - Clippings: China Guerrilla Warfare, 1935-1938 (Text 3: 3)
  - Clippings: Japanese Aggression in China, 1934-1937 (Text 3: 4)
  - Communism in China, 1931-1935 (Text 3: 5)
  - Dorothea Gabel, 1938-1961 (Text 3: 6)
  - English Translations of Chinese Articles, 1928-1934 (Text 3: 7)
  - English Translations of Chinese Articles, 1934 (Text 3: 8)
  - Inner Mongolia and Chinese Communism, 1933-1936 (Text 3: 9)
  - Japan, 1934-1936 (Text 3: 10)
  - Red Army and Communist Activities in JIangxi and Sichuan, 1934-1937 (Text 3: 11)
- Writings, 1928-1937
  - "China's '400' Million", undated (Text 4: 1)
  - "Comparative Table of Communist Program for China in 1928 and 1935", 1928-1935 (Text 4: 2)
  - "Conflicting Forces in China", undated (Text 4: 3)
  - Drafts, undated (Text 4: 4)
  - "Forum: Understanding China", 1936 (Text 4: 5)
  - "Japanese Imperialism versus Chinese 'Communism': Notes on Contrasting Policies,", undated (Text 4: 6)
  - "Notes on Local Government in China,", undated (Text 4: 7)
  - "Notes on Unrest in China", undated (Text 4: 8)
  - "'Red Baiting' in North China, Communism in Kiangsi, and Communism in Sezchuan,", 1934 (Text 4: 9)
  - "Rotten Gentry of China,", 1937 (Text 4: 10)
  - "Student Organization at Yenching,", undated (Text 4: 11)
  - "The Actual Strength of the Red Army,", undated (Text 4: 12)
  - "The Chinese Communist Occupation,", undated (Text 4: 13)
  - "The International Relations of Manchuria,", undated (Text 4: 14)
  - "The Real Rulers of China,", undated (Text 4: 15)
  - "The Szechuan Soviet Armies,", undated (Text 4: 16)
  - "When Chinese Reds Move In,", 1936 (Text 4: 17)
  - "Where Japan Rules in China,", 1937 (Text 4: 18)
  - "Why Peasants Hate Government,", undated (Text 4: 19)
  - "Within Chinese Red Areas,", 1937 (Text 4: 20)
  - "Within Chinese communist Territory,", undated (Text 4: 21)
  - Yenching University Course Syllabus, 1932-1933 (Text 4: 22)